<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-v6ops-ula-usage-considerations-03"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ULA Usage">Considerations For Using Unique Local
    Addresses</title>

    <author fullname="Bing Liu" initials="B." surname="Liu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus, No.156 Beiqing Road</street>

          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing, 100095</city>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>leo.liubing@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sheng Jiang" initials="S." surname="Jiang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus, No.156 Beiqing Road</street>

          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing, 100095</city>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jiangsheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
<author fullname="Nick Buraglio" initials="N." surname="Buraglio">
      <organization>ForwardingPlane, LLC</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>buraglio@forwardingplane.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="13" month="March" year="2017"/>

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides considerations for using IPv6 Unique Local
      Addresses (ULAs). Based on an analysis of different ULA usage scenarios,
      this document identifies use cases where ULA addresses are helpful as
      well as potential problems caused by using them.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Unique Local Addresses (ULA) is defined in <xref target="RFC4193"/>,
      and it is an alternative to site-local address (deprecated in <xref
      target="RFC3879"/>). ULAs have the following features:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="-">Automatically Generated</t>

          <t>ULA prefixes can be automatically generated using the algorithms
          described in <xref target="RFC4193"/>. This feature allows automatic
          prefix allocation. Thus one can get a network working immediately
          without applying for prefix(es) from an RIR/LIR (Regional Internet
          Registry/Local Internet Registry).</t>

          <t hangText="-">Globally Unique</t>

          <t hangText="">ULAs are defined as a global scope address space.
          However, they are not intended to be used globally on the public
          Internet; in contrast, they are mostly used locally, for example, in
          isolated networks, internal networks, or VPNs.</t>

          <t hangText="">ULAs are intended to have an extremely low
          probability of collision. The randomization of 40 bits in a ULA
          prefix is considered sufficient enough to ensure a high degree of
          uniqueness (refer to <xref target="RFC4193"/> Section 3.2.3 for
          details) and simplifies merging of networks by avoiding the need to
          renumber overlapping IP address space. </t>

          <t hangText="-">Provider Independent Address Space</t>

          <t hangText="">ULAs can be used for internal communications even
          without Internet connectivity. They need no registration, so they
          can support on-demand usage and do not carry any RIR/LIR burden of
          documentation or fees.</t>

          <t hangText="-">Well Known Prefix</t>

          <t hangText="">The prefixes of ULAs are well known thus they are
          easily identified and filtered.</t>
        </list>This document aims to introduce the usage of ULAs in various
      scenarios, provide some operational considerations, and clarify the
      advantages and disadvantages of the usage in each scenario. Thus, the
      administrators could choose to use ULAs in a certain way that considered
      benificial for them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/> when they appear in ALL CAPS. When these words are
      not in ALL CAPS (such as "should" or "Should"), they have their usual
      English meanings, and are not to be interpreted as <xref
      target="RFC2119"/> key words.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="General Considerations For Using ULAs">
      <section title="Do Not Treat ULA Equal to RFC1918">
        <t>ULA and <xref target="RFC1918"/> are similar in some aspects. The
        most obvious one is as described in Section 3.1.3 that ULA provides an
        internal address independence capability in IPv6 that is similar to
        how <xref target="RFC1918"/> is commonly used. ULA allows
        administrators to configure the internal network of each platform the
        same way it is configured in IPv4. Many organizations have security
        policies and architectures based around the local-only routing of
        <xref target="RFC1918"/> addresses and those policies may directly map
        to ULA <xref target="RFC4864"/>.</t>

        <t>But this does not mean that ULA is equal to an IPv6 version of
        <xref target="RFC1918"/> deployment. <xref target="RFC1918"/> usually
        combines with NAT/NAPT for global connectivity. But it is not
        necessary to combine ULAs with any kind of NAT. Operators can use ULA
        for local communications along with global addresses for global
        communications (see <xref target="ULAPA"/>). This is a big advantage
        brought by default support of multiple-addresses-per-interface feature
        in IPv6. (People may still have a requirement for NAT with ULA, this
        is discussed in <xref target="ULAonly"/>. But people also need to keep
        in mind that ULA is not intentionally designed for this kind of use
        case.)</t>

        <t>Another important difference is the ability to merge two ULA
        networks without renumbering (because of the uniqueness), which is a
        big advantage over <xref target="RFC1918"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Using ULAs in a Limited Scope">
        <t>A ULA is by definition a prefix that is never advertised outside a
        given domain, and is used within that domain by agreement of those
        networked by the domain.</t>

        <t>So when using ULAs in a network, the administrators need to clearly
        set the scope of the ULAs and configure ACLs on relevant border
        routers to block them out of the scope. And if internal DNS is
        enabled, the administrators might also need to use internal-only DNS
        names for ULAs and might need to split the DNS so that the internal
        DNS server includes records that are not presented in the external DNS
        server.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Analysis and Operational Considerations for Scenarios Using ULAs">
      <section anchor="isolat" title="ULA-only in Isolated Networks">
        <t>IP is used ubiquitously. Some networks like industrial control bus
        (e.g. <xref target="RS-485"/>, <xref target="SCADA"/>, or even
        non-networked digital interfaces like <xref target="MIL-STD-1397"/>
        have begun to use IP. In these kinds of networks, the system may lack
        the ability to communicate with the public networks.</t>

        <t>As another example, there may be some networks in which the
        equipment has the technical capability to connect to the Internet, but
        is prohibited by administration. These networks may include data
        center networks, separate financial networks, lab networks.
        machine-to-machine (e.g. vehicle networks), sensor networks, or even
        normal LANs, and can include very large numbers of addresses.</t>

        <t>ULA is a straightforward way to assign the IP addresses in the
        kinds of networks just described, with minimal administrative cost or
        burden. Also, ULAs fit in multiple subnet scenarios, in which each
        subnet has its own ULA prefix. For example, when assigning vehicles
        with ULAs, it is then possible to separate in-vehicle embedded
        networks into different subnets depending on real-time situation.</t>

        <t>However, each isolated network has the possibility to be connected
        in the future. Administrators need to consider the following before
        deciding whether to use ULAs: <list style="symbols">
            <t>If the network eventually connects to another isolated or
            private network, the potential for address collision arises.
            However, if the ULAs were generated in the standard way, this will
            not be a big problem.</t>

            <t>If the network eventually connects to the global Internet, then
            the operator will need to add a new global prefix and ensure that
            the address selection policy is properly set up on all
            interfaces.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Operational considerations:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Prefix generation: randomly generated according to the
            algorithms defined in <xref target="RFC4193"/> or manually
            assigned. Normally, automatic generation of the prefixes is
            recommended, following <xref target="RFC4193"/>. If there are some
            specific reasons that call for manual assignment, administrators
            have to plan the prefixes carefully to avoid collision.</t>

            <t>Prefix announcement: in some cases, networks might need to
            announce prefixes to each other. For example, in vehicle networks
            with infrastructure-less settings such as Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V)
            communication, prior knowledge of the respective prefixes is
            unlikely. Hence, a prefix announcement mechanism is needed to
            enable inter-vehicle communications based on IP. As one
            possibility, such announcements could rely on extensions to the
            Router Advertisement message of the Neighbor Discovery Protocol
            (e.g., <xref target="I-D.petrescu-autoconf-ra-based-routing"/> and
            <xref target="I-D.jhlee-mext-mnpp"/>).</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ULAPA" title="ULA+PA in Connected Networks">
        <t>Two classes of network might need to use ULA with PA (Provider
        Aggregated) addresses:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Home network. Home networks are normally assigned with one or
            more globally routed PA prefixes to connect to the uplink of an
            ISP. In addition, they may need internal routed networking even
            when the ISP link is down. Then ULA is a proper tool to fit the
            requirement. <xref target="RFC7084"/> requires the CPE to support
            ULA. Note: ULAs provide more benefit for multiple-segment home
            networks; for home networks containing only one segment,
            link-local addresses are better alternatives.</t>

            <t>Enterprise network. An enterprise network is usually a managed
            network with one or more PA prefixes or with a PI prefix, all of
            which are globally routed. The ULA can be used to improve internal
            connectivity and make it more resilient, or to isolate certain
            functions like OAM for servers.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Benefits of Using ULAs in this scenario:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Separated local communication plane: for either home networks
            or enterprise networks, the main purpose of using ULAs along with
            PA addresses is to provide a logically local routing plane
            separated from the global routing plane. The benefit is to ensure
            stable and specific local communication regardless of the ISP
            uplink failure. This benefit is especially meaningful for the home
            network or for private OAM function in an enterprise.</t>

            <t>Renumbering: in some special cases such as renumbering,
            enterprise administrators may want to avoid the need to renumber
            their internal-only, private nodes when they have to renumber the
            PA addresses of the rest of the network because they are changing
            ISPs, because the ISP has restructured its address allocations, or
            for some other reason. In these situations, ULA is an effective
            tool for addressing internal-only nodes. Even public nodes can
            benefit from ULA for renumbering, on their internal interfaces.
            When renumbering, as <xref target="RFC4192"/> suggests, old
            prefixes continue to be valid until the new prefix(es) is(are)
            stable. In the process of adding new prefix(es) and deprecating
            old prefix(es), it is not easy to keep local communication
            disentangled from global routing plane change. If we use ULAs for
            local communication, the separated local routing plane can isolate
            the effects of global routing change.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Drawbacks:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Operational Complexity: there are some arguments that in
            practice the use of ULA+PA creates additional operational
            complexity. This is not a ULA-specific problem; the
            multiple-addresses-per-interface is an important feature of IPv6
            protocol. Nevertheless, running multiple prefixes needs more
            operational consideration than running a single one.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Operational considerations:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Default Routing: connectivity may be broken if ULAs are used as
            default route. When using RIO (Route Information Option) in <xref
            target="RFC4191"/>, specific routes can be added without a default
            route, thus avoiding bad user experience due to timeouts on ICMPv6
            redirects. This behavior was well documented in <xref
            target="RFC7084"/> as rule ULA-5 "An IPv6 CE router MUST NOT
            advertise itself as a default router with a Router Lifetime
            greater than zero whenever all of its configured and delegated
            prefixes are ULA prefixes." and along with rule L-3 "An IPv6 CE
            router MUST advertise itself as a router for the delegated
            prefix(es) (and ULA prefix if configured to provide ULA
            addressing) using the "Route Information Option" specified in
            Section 2.3 of <xref target="RFC4191"/>. This advertisement is
            independent of having or not having IPv6 connectivity on the WAN
            interface.". However, it needs to be noticed that current OSes
            don't all support <xref target="RFC4191"/>.</t>

            <t>SLAAC/DHCPv6 co-existing: Since SLAAC and DHCPv6 might be
            enabled in one network simultaneously; the administrators need to
            carefully plan how to assign ULA and PA prefixes in accordance
            with the two mechanisms. The administrators need to know the
            current issue of the SLAAC/DHCPv6 interaction (please refer to
            <xref target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-dhcpv6-slaac-problem"/> for
            details).</t>

            <t>Address selection: As mentioned in <xref target="RFC5220"/>,
            there is a possibility that the longest matching rule will not be
            able to choose the correct address between ULAs and global unicast
            addresses for correct intra-site and extra-site communication.
            <xref target="RFC6724"/> claims that a site-specific policy entry
            can be used to cause ULAs within a site to be preferred over
            global addresses.</t>

            <t>DNS relevant: if administrators choose not to do reverse DNS
            delegation inside of their local control of ULA prefixes, a
            significant amount of information about the ULA population may
            leak to the outside world. Because reverse queries will be made
            and naturally routed to the global reverse tree, so external
            parties will be exposed to the existence of a population of ULA
            addresses. <xref target="ULA-IN-WILD"/> provides more detailed
            situations on this issue. Administrators may need a split DNS to
            separate the queries from internal and external for ULA entries
            and GUA entries.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ULAonly" title="ULA-Only in Connected Networks">
        <t>In theory, a site numbered with ULAs only can get connected via a
        NPTv6<xref target="RFC6296"/> (which is an experimental specification
        that provides a stateless one-to-one mapping between internal
        addresses and external addresses) or application-layer proxy. This
        approach could get provider independent addresses or get connected
        from the isolated stage without applying to any RIRs/LIRs. This might
        make small organizations saving time and address fee.</t>

        <t>However, this approach breaks the end-to-end transparence. People
        have suffered from the NAT/Proxy middle boxes so much in the IPv4 ear,
        there is no reason to continue the suffering when IPv6 is available.
        This document does not consider ULA+NPTv6/Proxy as a good choice for
        normal cases. Rather, this document considers ULA+PA (Provider
        Aggregated) as a better approach to connect to the global network when
        ULAs are expected to be retained.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Some Specific Use Cases">
        <t>Along with the general scenarios, this section provides some
        specific use cases that could benefit from using ULA.</t>

        <section title="Special Routing">
          <t>For various reasons the administrators may want to have private
          routing be controlled and separated from other routing. For example,
          in the business-to-business case described in <xref
          target="I-D.baker-v6ops-b2b-private-routing"/>, two companies might
          want to use direct connectivity that only connects stated machines,
          such as a silicon foundry with client engineers that use it. A ULA
          provides a simple way to assign prefixes that would be used in
          accordance with an agreement between the parties.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Used as Identifier">
          <t>ULAs could be self-generated and easily grabbed from the standard
          IPv6 stack. And ULAs don't need to be changed as the GUA prefixes
          do. So they are very suitable to be used as identifiers by the up
          layer applications. And since ULA is not intended to be globally
          routed, it is not harmful to the routing system.</t>

          <t>Such kind of benefit has been utilized in real implementations.
          For example, in <xref target="RFC6281"/>, the protocol BTMM (Back To
          My Mac) needs to assign a topology-independent identifier to each
          client host according to the following considerations:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>TCP connections between two end hosts wish to survive in
              network changes.</t>

              <t>Sometimes one needs a constant identifier to be associated
              with a key so that the Security Association can survive the
              location changes.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>It needs to be noticed again that in theory ULA has the
          possibility of collision. However, the probability is desirably
          small enough and can be ignored in most cases when ULAs are used as
          identifiers.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv4 Co-existence Considerations">
        <t>Generally, this document does not consider IPv4 to be in scope. But
        regarding ULA, there is a special case needs to be recognized, which
        is described in Section 3.2.2 of <xref target="RFC5220"/>. When an
        enterprise has IPv4 Internet connectivity but does not yet have IPv6
        Internet connectivity, and the enterprise wants to provide site-local
        IPv6 connectivity, a ULA is the best choice for site-local IPv6
        connectivity. Each employee host will have both an IPv4 global or
        private address and a ULA. Here, when this host tries to connect to an
        outside node that has registered both A and AAAA records in the DNS,
        the host will choose AAAA as the destination address and the ULA for
        the source address according to the IPv6 preference of the default
        policy table defined in the old address selection standard <xref
        target="RFC3484"/>. This will clearly result in a connection failure.
        The new address selection standard <xref target="RFC6724"/> has
        corrected this behavior by preferring IPv4 than ULAs in the default
        policy table. However, there are still lots of hosts using the old
        standard <xref target="RFC3484"/>, thus this could be an issue in real
        networks.</t>

        <t>Happy Eyeballs <xref target="RFC6555"/> solves this connection
        failure problem, but unwanted timeouts will obviously lower the user
        experience. One possible approach to eliminating the timeouts is to
        deprecate the IPv6 default route and simply configure a scoped route
        on hosts (in the context of this document, only configure the ULA
        prefix routes). Another alternative is to configure IPv4 preference on
        the hosts, and not include DNS A records but only AAAA records for the
        internal nodes in the internal DNS server. Then outside nodes have
        both A and AAAA records and can be connected through IPv4 as default
        and internal nodes can always connect through IPv6. But since IPv6
        preference is default, changing the default in all nodes is not
        suitable at scale.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations regarding ULAs, in general, please refer to
      the ULA specification <xref target="RFC4193"/>. Also refer to <xref
      target="RFC4864"/>, which shows how ULAs help with local network
      protection.</t>

      <t>As mentioned in <xref target="ULAPA"/>, when using NPTv6, the
      administrators need to know where the firewall is located to set proper
      filtering rules.</t>

      <t>Also as mentioned in <xref target="ULAPA"/>, if administrators choose
      not to do reverse DNS delegation inside their local control of ULA
      prefixes, a significant amount of information about the ULA population
      may leak to the outside world.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many valuable comments were received in the IETF v6ops WG mail list,
      especially from Cameron Byrne, Fred Baker, Brian Carpenter, Lee Howard,
      Victor Kuarsingh, Alexandru Petrescu, Mikael Abrahamsson, Tim Chown, Jen
      Linkova, Christopher Palmer Jong-Hyouk Lee, Mark Andrews, Lorenzo
      Colitti, Ted Lemon, Joel Jaeggli, David Farmer, Doug Barton, Owen
      Delong, Gert Doering, Bill Jouris, Bill Cerveny, Dave Thaler, Nick
      Hilliard, Jan Zorz, Randy Bush, Anders Brandt, , Sofiane Imadali and
      Wesley George.</t>

      <t>Some test of using ULA in the lab was done by our research partner
      BNRC-BUPT (Broad Network Research Centre in Beijing University of Posts
      and Telecommunications). Thanks for the work of Prof. Xiangyang Gong and
      student Dengjia Xu.</t>

      <t>Tom Taylor did a language review and revision throught the whole
      document. The authors appreciate a lot for his help.</t>

      <t>This document was produced using the xml2rfc tool <xref
      target="RFC2629"/> (initially prepared using
      2-Word-v2.0.template.dot.).</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
    <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC2629;
      &RFC4193;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1918;
      &RFC2993;
      &RFC3027;
      &RFC3484;
      &RFC3879;
      &RFC4191;
      &RFC4192;
      &RFC4864;
      &RFC5220;
      &RFC5902;
      &RFC6052;
      &RFC6281;
      &RFC6296;
      &RFC6555;
      &RFC6724;
      &RFC7084;
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-v6ops-dhcpv6-slaac-problem'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.baker-v6ops-b2b-private-routing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.petrescu-autoconf-ra-based-routing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.jhlee-mext-mnpp'?>

      <reference anchor="RS-485">
        <front>
          <title>Electronic Industries Association (1983). Electrical
          Characteristics of Generators and Receivers for Use in Balanced
          Multipoint Systems. EIA Standard RS-485.</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MIL-STD-1397">
        <front>
          <title>Military Standard, Input/Output Interfaces, Standard Digital
          Data, Navy Systems (MIL-STD-1397B), 3 March 1989</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SCADA">
        <front>
          <title>Boyer, Stuart A. (2010). SCADA Supervisory Control and Data
          Acquisition. USA: ISA - International Society of Automation.</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ULA-IN-WILD">
        <front>
          <title>G. Michaelson,
          "conference.apnic.net/data/36/apnic-36-ula_1377495768.pdf"</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
